<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>fedora on Nasir Hussain</title>
    <link>https://nasirhm.github.io/categories/fedora/</link>
    <description>Recent content in fedora on Nasir Hussain</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 02:56:46 +0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nasirhm.github.io/categories/fedora/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gotta Badge &#39;Em All: Fedora Social Panda</title>
      <link>https://nasirhm.github.io/2020/badge-fedora-social-hour/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 02:56:46 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nasirhm.github.io/2020/badge-fedora-social-hour/</guid>
      <description>This article is originally inspired by Justin W. Flory&amp;rsquo;s Gotta Badge `em All series about how to earn specific Fedora badges.
Fedora Social Panda: What&amp;rsquo;s it about? How It all Started is, As COVID-19 is getting pretty real and resulting in people performing social distancing, shelter-in-place &amp;amp; Lockdowns resulting in most of us feeling pretty isolated so out Fedora Project Leader Matthew Miller &amp;amp; Fedora Project Contributor Neal Gompa had the idea to have a Fedora Social Hour where folks could Chat &amp;amp; get a little e-human contact and conversation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gotta Badge &#39;Em All: Fedora &amp; CentOS Social @ Summit 2020</title>
      <link>https://nasirhm.github.io/2020/badge-fedora-centos-social-summit20/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 06:19:13 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nasirhm.github.io/2020/badge-fedora-centos-social-summit20/</guid>
      <description>This article is inspired by Justin W. Flory&amp;rsquo;s Gotta Badge `em All series about how to earn specific Fedora badges.
Fedora &amp;amp; CentOS Social @ Summit 2020: What&amp;rsquo;s it about? The Fedora &amp;amp; CentOS Social @ Summit 2020 badge is categorized as a &amp;ldquo;Event Badge&amp;rdquo; and it&amp;rsquo;s defined in this Pagure ticket But what it&amp;rsquo;s all about?
In short, the Fedora &amp;amp; CentOS Social @ Summit 2020 badge is awarded to people who attended the Red Hat Virtual Summit 2020 &amp;amp; Participated in The Fedora Chatroom on April 28-29.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Fedora QA - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://nasirhm.github.io/2020/getting-started-with-fedora-qa-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 17:29:03 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nasirhm.github.io/2020/getting-started-with-fedora-qa-part-1/</guid>
      <description>What is SQA (Quality Assurance) ? According to Wikipedia : Software quality assurance (SQA) is a means of monitoring the software engineering processes and methods used to ensure proper quality. SQA encompasses the entire software development process, including requirements definition, software design, coding, code reviews, source code control, software configuration management, testing, release management and product integration. It is organized into goals, commitments, abilities, activities, measurements and verification.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to FOSS and Fedora Project</title>
      <link>https://nasirhm.github.io/talks/intro-foss-and-fedora-15-02-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 01:29:42 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nasirhm.github.io/talks/intro-foss-and-fedora-15-02-20/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to Free and Open Source Software and Fedora Project Originally presented at Fedora 31 Release Party Karachi on 15th Feb 2020 in Karachi, Pakistan
Key points  What is FOSS, Free and Open Source Software Perks of contributing to a FOSS What is Fedora Project  Four Foundations   Where to contribute How to start contributing  Slides Google Slides</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>